Guide to the Katherine Camp Mayhew papers, [ca. 1896-1949],
Mayhew, Katherine Camp papers, [ca. 1896-1949]
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Katherine Camp Mayhew papers, [ca. 1896-1949], [ca. 1896-1902] (bulk)
6561
Katherine Camp. Mayhew
5.7 cubic ft.
Correspondence, drafts, notes, logbooks
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Papers consist of source material gathered for THE DEWEY SCHOOL: THE LABORATORY SCHOOL OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO, 1896-1903, a book by Katherine Camp Mayhew and her sister Anna Camp Edwards, a colleague at the school. Included are twelve logbooks containing weekly reports on curriculum, classroom activities, and student progress, 1896-1902; drafts, notes, and correspondence relating to specific chapters of the book, ca. 1896-1934; syllabi, course outlines, clippings of articles about the school, minutes of teachers' meetings, lists of students and teachers, photographs of children, and printed material. Of note are notes and correspondence by John Dewey relating to the preparation of the book (in which he had a hand), and memoranda, reports, syllabi, articles, and miscellaneous writings by Dewey, ca. 1890s-1930, relating to the running of the Laboratory School, courses at Teachers College, Columbia University, and miscellaneous matters.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Teacher, author.
Mayhew taught at the Laboratory School of the University of Chicago.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Papers consist of source material gathered for THE DEWEY SCHOOL: THE LABORATORY SCHOOL OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO, 1896-1903, a book by Katherine Camp Mayhew and her sister Anna Camp Edwards, a colleague at the school. Included are twelve logbooks containing weekly reports on curriculum, classroom activities, and student progress, 1896-1902; drafts, notes, and correspondence relating to specific chapters of the book, ca. 1896-1934; syllabi, course outlines, clippings of articles about the school, minutes of teachers' meetings, lists of students and teachers, photographs of children, and printed material. Of note are notes and correspondence by John Dewey relating to the preparation of the book (in which he had a hand), and memoranda, reports, syllabi, articles, and miscellaneous writings by Dewey, ca. 1890s-1930, relating to the running of the Laboratory School, courses at Teachers College, Columbia University, and miscellaneous matters.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Mayhew, Katherine Camp.; Dewey, John, 1859-1952.; Edwards, Anna Camp, 1876-1956.; Columbia University.Teachers College.; University of Chicago.University Elementary School.
Subjects:
Laboratory schools--Illinois--Chicago.; Education--Experimental methods.; Education--Illinois--Chicago.; Education--Study and teaching.; Women teachers.; Women authors.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photoprints.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
There is a gap in the box numbering sequence: numbers skip from Box 4 to Box 11.
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. The Dewey Logs
  - Elementary School - school plan and notes, news clippings about the school, 1896-1899, April and June 1900 (Box 1)
  - History - Groups IV-VI, 1899-1901 (Box 1)
  - Science - Groups IV-IX and history and science, 1899-1901 (Box 1)
  - Math and Science - Groups III-X, 1899-1901 (Box 2)
  - History - Groups IV-X Elementary Record Nos. 2, 7 & 8, 1900-1901 (Box 2)
  - Quarterly Reports - various subjects; list of students enrolled 1899-1902; child study, Group IV, 1901-1902 (Box 2)
  - Group Reports - all subjects and groups, 1901-1902 (Box 3)
  - Sewing; Children's Record; History of Ab (story created by pupils about cave people) typed children's essays, 1899-1901, 1896-1897 (Box 3)
  - Cooking - subprimary-Group X, 1899-1900 (Box 3)
  - Cooking - all groups, 1900-1901 (Box 4)
  - All primary - suggested outlines; curriculum for subprimary and kindergarten; "Three Years of the University Elementary School"; outlines for courses, 1899-1901 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous - instructions for children's health; teachers' circular 1899; reports on courses; Play: "Colonial Days in Virginia"; outline of history courses; class schedule, 1899-1901 (Box 4)
  - "The University Elementary School", n.d. (Box 4)
  - "Three Years of the University Elementary School", January 1899 (Box 4)
  - University Record, excerpts, 1897-1898 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - University Record, 1898-1899 (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Series II. Source Material for Specific Chapters
  - Chapter Outlines, 1896-1900, 1930 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Chapter I, "General History" - notes, drafts, teacher lists, 1896-1902 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Chapter I, "General History" - notes, drafts, teacher lists, 1896-1902 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Chapter I, "General History" - drafts, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Chapter 1, "General History" - published material describing school, 1896-1902 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Chapters II & III - articles relating to chapters on curriculum, 1895-n.d. (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Chapters II & III - notes and drafts, articles by John and Alice Dewey on curriculum (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Chapters II & III - on curriculum drafts, November 18, 1930 & n.d. (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Chapters II & III - on curriculum drafts, November 18, 1930 & n.d. (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Chapter III, "Experimental Practices Developing the Curriculum"- drafts, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Chapter III, "Experimental Practices Developing the Curriculum"- drafts, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Chapter III, "Experimental Practices Developing the Curriculum"- drafts, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Chapter IV, "Household Occupations" - notes, 1896-1902 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Chapter IV, "Household Occupations" - article by Katherine B. Camp, October 1901 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Chapter IV, "Household Occupations" - drafts, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Chapters IV & V on household occupations - excerpts not used - notes and drafts, 1896-1902 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Chapters IV & V on household occupations - excerpts not used - notes and drafts, 1896-1902 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Chapters IV & V on household occupations - excerpts not used - notes and drafts, 1896-1902 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Chapters IV & V on household occupations - excerpts not used - notes and drafts, 1896-1902 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Chapter V, "Social Occupations Serving the Household" - notes, 1898-1901 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Chapter V, "Social Occupations Serving the Household" - notes and drafts, 1896-1901 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Chapter V, "Social Occupations Serving the Household" - notes and drafts, 1896-1901 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Chapter V, "Social Occupations Serving the Household" - notes and drafts, 1896-1901 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Chapter V, "Social Occupations Serving the Household" - notes and drafts, 1896-1901 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Chapters V & VI - drafts, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Chapter VI, "Progress Through Invention and Discovery" - notes, 1898-1899 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Chapter VI, "Progress Through Invention and Discovery" - notes, 1898-1899 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Chapter VI, "Progress Through Invention and Discovery" - notes, 1898-1899 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Chapter VI, "Progress Through Invention and Discovery" - notes, 1898-1899 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Chapter VI, "Progress Through Invention and Discovery" - notes, 1898-1899 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Chapter VI-X, XVI on teaching history; Thesis by Laura L. Runyon with correspondence, 1906 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Chapter VII, "Progress Through Exploration and Discovery" - reports on Group V, 1898-1902 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Chapter VII, "Progress Through Exploration and Discovery" - reports on Group V, 1898-1902 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Chapter VII, "Progress Through Exploration and Discovery" - notes, 1898-1902 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Chapter VII, "Progress Through Exploration and Discovery" - drafts (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Chapter VIII, "Local History" - notes and drafts, 1898-1901 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Chapter VIII, "Local History" - notes and drafts, 1898-1901 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Chapter VIII, "Local History" - notes and drafts, 1898-1901 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Chapter VIII, "Local History" - notes and drafts, 1898-1901 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Chapter VIII, "Local History" - notes and drafts, 1898-1901 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Chapter IX, "Colonial History and the Revolution" - excerpts not used, 1898-1902 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Chapter IX, "Colonial History and the Revolution" - excerpts not used, 1898-1902 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Chapter IX & X on colonists - notes and drafts, 1896-1899 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Chapter X, "European Background of the Colonists" - notes and drafts, 1898-1902 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Chapter X, "European Background of the Colonists" - notes and drafts, 1898-1902 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Chapter X, "European Background of the Colonists" - notes and drafts, 1898-1902 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Chapter X, "European Background of the Colonists" - unused material - notes and drafts, 1898-1902 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Chapter X, "European Background of the Colonists" - unused material - notes and drafts, 1898-1902 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Chapter X, "European Background of the Colonists" - unused material - notes and drafts, 1898-1902 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Chapter X, "European Background of the Colonists" - unused material - notes and drafts, 1898-1902 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Chapter XI, "Experiments in Specialized Activities" - notes, 1898-1900 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Chapter XI, "Experiments in Specialized Activities" - printed extract from Elementary School Teacher and notes, 1902-1903 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Chapter XI, "Experiments in Specialized Activities" - draft, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Chapter XII, "Experiments in Specialized Activities" - notes, n.d., 1901 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Chapter XII, "Experiments in Specialized Activities" - notes, draft, suggested titles for book, 1899-1901 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Chapter XII, "Experiments in Specialized Activities" - notes, draft, suggested titles for book, 1899-1901 (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Chapter XIII, "Experiments in Specialized Activities " - notes and Chapter XIV, "Principles of Growth Guiding Selection of Activities" - draft, revised copy, n.d. & October 1934 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Chapter XIV, "Principles of Growth Guiding Selection of Activities" - drafts including one by Dewey, August 1930 & October 1934 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Chapter XV, "Experimental Activities Developing Scientific Method and Concepts" - notes and drafts, 1897-1904, 1930 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Chapter XV, "Experimental Activities Developing Scientific Method and Concepts" - notes and drafts, 1897-1904, 1930 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Chapter XV, "Experimental Activities Developing Scientific Method and Concepts" - notes and drafts, 1897-1904, 1930 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Chapter XV, "Experimental Activities Developing Scientific Method and Concepts" - notes and drafts, 1897-1904, 1930 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Chapter XV, "Experimental Activities Developing Scientific Method and Concepts" - notes and drafts, 1897-1904, 1930 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Chapter XV, "Experimental Activities Developing Scientific Method and Concepts" - notes and drafts, 1897-1904, 1930 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Chapter XV, "Experimental Activities Developing Scientific Method and Concepts" - articles pertaining to chapter, June & September 1903 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Chapter XV, "Experimental Activities Developing Scientific Method and Concepts" - notes, 1899-1902 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Chapter XVI, "Experimental Activities Developing Origins and Backgrounds of Social Life" - notes and drafts, April 1900-n.d. (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Chapter XVII, "Experimental Activities Developing Skills in Communications and Expression" - notes, drafts, article from Elementary School Record 1900, 1930-1932 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Chapter XVII, "Experimental Activities Developing Skills in Communication and Expression" - articles and drafts, 1898, 1903 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Chapter XVII, "Experimental Activities Developing Skills in Communication and Expression" - articles and drafts, 1898, 1903 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Chapter XVIII, "Teachers and School Organization" - drafts and correspondence, August 1929 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Chapter XVIII, "Teachers and School Organization" - material cut from chapter (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Chapter XVIII, "Teachers and School Organization" - material cut from chapter (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Chapter XIX, "Parents and Children" - notes, 1900 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Chapter XIX, "Parents and Children" - notes, lists of parents, courses, teachers, notes on teachers meeting, correspondence (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Chapter XIX, "Parents and Children" - photographs (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Chapter XIX, " Parents and Children" - notes, drafts, correspondence (signed) from Dewey, April 22, 1901 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Chapter XIX, "Parents and Children" - teachers notes on students, correspondence, 1900-1903, 1929 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Chapter XIX, "Parents and Children" - correspondence, lists of parents and children, 1900-1901, 1928-1930, 1933 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Chapter XIX, "Parents and Children" - notes and drafts (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Chapter XIX, "Parents and Children" - notes and drafts (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Chapter XX, "Evaluation of Principles and Practices" - notes and articles, 1896-1897, 1904 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Chapter XX, "Evaluation of Principles and Practices" - notes and articles, 1896-1897, 1904 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Chapter XX, "Evaluation of Principles and Practices" - notes and drafts (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Chapter XX, "Evaluation of Principles and Practices" - notes and drafts (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Appendix I, "The Evolution of Mr. Dewey's Principles of Education" - draft (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Appendix II, "Theory of the Chicago Experiment" - draft written by John Dewey (Box 18, Folder 9)
- Series III. Miscellaneous Source Material
  - The Elementary School Teacher, May 1903 (Box 19)
  - The Elementary School Teacher, June 1903 (Box 19)
  - The Elementary School Teacher, September 1903 (Box 19)
  - The Elementary School Teacher, October 1903 (Box 19)
  - The Elementary School Teacher, November 1903 (Box 19)
  - The Elementary School Teacher, December 1903 (Box 20)
  - The Elementary School Teacher, January 1904 (Box 20)
  - The Elementary School Teacher, March 1904 (Box 20)
  - The Elementary School Teacher, May 1904 (Box 20)
  - Ella Flagg Young: Contributions to Education No. I: Isolation in the School; Review of Isolation in the School; Contributions to Education No. VI: Some Types of Modern Educational Theory; Partial review of Dewey's Democracy and Education, 1901-1907 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Alice C. Dewey: notes, syllabus: Elementary Education, 1903, 1907 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Source articles by teachers, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - William H. Kilpatrick: The Project Method, October 12, 1918 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous articles by George H. Mead and S. F. MacLennan, April 1898 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Notes on source material; correspondence (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Stories by pupils, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - College Curriculum including College of Education, 1904, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - News clippings on education, etc., 1939-1947, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous material; notes and drafts (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous material; notes and drafts (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous material; notes and drafts (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous material; notes and drafts (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous material - correspondence, syllabus - Creative Teaching, notes, May 16, 1933 & n.d. (Box 21, Folder 14)
- Series IV. Writing of John Dewey
  - Chapter I, "General History" - Dewey's 1st report after merger of Laboratory School with School of Education, 1902-1903 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Chapter 1, "General History" - articles by Dewey mentioned in footnote pp. 4-5, 1895-1897 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Chapter 1, "General History" - articles by Dewey mentioned in footnote pp. 4-5, 1895-1897 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Chapter I, "General History" - notes, prospectus, drafts, one by John Dewey; one by Alice Dewey, 1899-1900 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Notes of Conference with Dewey, September 1930 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous writing of John Dewey, 1896-1900 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous writing of John Dewey, 1896-1900 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous writing of John Dewey, 1900 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - John Dewey: History of Education: Volumes I-VII; Psychology for Teachers: Volumes I-IV, 1907 (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - John Dewey at 90 - articles, October 1949 (Box 22, Folder 10)